Criswell (Narrator) was born
Jeron King Criswell...
...on August 18, 1907.
Criswell was a friend of Ed Wood's
and was in two more of Ed's movies:
"Night of the Ghouls" (1959)
again as narrator...
...and "Orgy of the Dead" (1965)
as the Lord of the Dead.
A popular prognosticator of the day
in 1969 he wrote a book:
"Criswell Predicts:
From Now To The Year 2000!"
Among his predictions was that
the world would end in 1999.
Criswell passed away on
October 4, 1982.
"Grave Robbers From Outer Space"
was the original title for "Plan 9."
It was changed
apparently at the insistence...
...of the Baptists who were
financing the picture.
Principal photography on "Plan 9"
took place in August 1956.
The film was completed (and
apparently previewed) in that year.
After more than two years
producer J. Edward Reynolds...
...eager to recover the costs
he had incurred from production...
...bought the rights to "Plan 9"
from Ed for one dollar.
When Reynolds finally found
a distributor...
...they required him to pay
all distribution costs himself.
But he finally got the film
released in July 1959.
Bela Lugosi was born
Béla Ferenc Dezso Blasko...
...on October 20, 1882.
He is credited in "Plan 9" as
"Ghoul Man."
The script however referred to him
as the "Dracula character"...
...and the film itself only calls him
"the old man."
Lugosi's career began in
Hungarian films in 1917.
It ended with "Plan 9" in 1959
despite his having died...
...on August 16, 1956.
On the right is our hero Jeff Trent,
played by Gregory Walcott.
Walcott was born Bernard Mattox
on January 13, 1928.
When "Plan 9" was made he had
already appeared on television...
...and made several movies.
"Plan 9" didn't hurt his career much.
He would work steadily
for the next two decades.
Walcott is known for heavily
disparaging "Plan 9" over the years.
This didn't stop him accepting
the part of a prospective investor...
...in Tim Burton's 1994
biopic "Ed Wood."
David De Mering (Danny) appeared
in one more film for Ed...
..."Night of the Ghouls" (1959).
The gravediggers are played by
two of the producers of "Plan 9":
Associate Producer Hugh Thomas Jr.
In the darker clothes...
...and Executive Producer
J. Edward Reynolds in the lighter.
Reynolds was Ed's landlord and had
secured the financing for "Plan"
...through his local church.
The footage of Bela Lugosi
that appears in "Plan"
...wasn't shot for
anything in particular.
It was basically Ed and Bela
improvising for the camera.
This footage was shot...
...at the home of fellow
Ed regular Tor Johnson.
Additional Bela footage existed
that Ed hoped to use...
...for another film:
"The Ghoul On The Moon."
When Ed went to retrieve
the footage, however...
...he found it had deteriorated,
so the film was not made.
The mourners are played by
Ben Frommer and Gloria Dea.
Frommer also appeared in Ed's
"Bride of the Monster“ (1955)."
Frommer was born on
June 12, 1913...
...and died on May 9, 1992,
having spent 40 years in showbiz.
Tor Johnson (Inspector Clay) was born
Tore Johansson on October 19, 1903.
He was a pro wrestler working
as "The Super Swedish Angel."
He also appeared for Ed
as the giant Lobo
in both "Bride of the Monster"
and "Night of the Ghouls."
Tor made many other films besides
the ones he did with Ed...
...including the Bob Hope/Bing Crosby
picture "Road to Rio" (1947)
and Hope's 1951 comedy
"The Lemon Drop Kid."
In "Ed Wood" (1994) Tor is
portrayed by another pro wrestler...
...George "The Animal" Steele.
Hopefully you enjoyed Tor's
dialogue from the previous scene.
They were the only words he ever
spoke in an Ed Wood film.
For the rest of "Plan 9" and in
his other Ed movies...
...Tor is completely mute.
Tor passed away on May 12, 1971.
Jeff's wife Paula Trent
is played by Mona McKinnon.
Mona met Ed when she went to
an open audition with Dolores Fuller.
Dolores wound up as Ed's girlfriend
and starred in several of his films.
Mona also worked with Ed
on other projects besides "Plan 9."
She appeared in a supporting role
in 1954's "Jail Bait"...
...and in footage shot
for the unfinished "Hellborn"...
that was incorporated into
"Night of the Ghouls."
Ed uses a classic 1950s description
of UFOs: "cigar-shaped."
This description usually came
from airline pilots
who would be seeing the UFO
from the side.
Coming up is one of the most
infamous moments in "Plan 9."
To the right you can see
the famous cardboard gravestone
knocked over by an extra's feet.
Standing in for Bela in this scene
(and for most of the film)
is Dr. Thomas Mason,
a chiropractor.
Mason would appear in
and co-finance Ed's next film...
..."Night of the Ghouls."
Duke Moore (Lieutenant Daniel Harper)
was born James Moore on July 15, 1913.
Moore was an old friend of Ed's
from their community theater days.
He first worked with Ed on TV
commercials in the late 1940s.
He would go on to appear
in six of Ed's films...
the last, "Take It Out In Trade,"
in 1970.
Moore passed away on
November 16, 1976.
The reverend is portrayed by
Reverend Lynn Lemon...
...the pastor at producer
J. Edward Reynolds' church.
To help secure the financing Ed was
baptized into Lemon's church...
...and used to call Lemon for
advice for years afterward.
Much has been written about
the flying saucers in "Plan 9."
Many have claimed that Ed used
anything from paper plates...
...to hubcaps to create them.
In the 1992 documentary
"Flying Saucers Over Hollywood"...
...it is demonstrated that they were
in fact store-bought model kits.
Tom Keene (Col. Tom Edwards) was born
George Duryea on December 30, 1896...
...in Rochester, New York.
Keene was a favorite of Ed's and
appeared in two other Ed projects:
1951's "The Sun Was Setting"
and the 1953 television pilot...
..."Crossroad Avenger:
The Adventures of the Tucson Kid."
Keene appeared in over
100 films and television shows...
...(mostly westerns).
"Plan 9" was Keene's last film.
He passed away on
August 4, 1963.
John "Bunny" Breckinridge (The Ruler)
was born John Cabell Breckinridge...
...on August 6, 1903.
He was a descendant of U.S.
Vice President John Breckinridge...
...who served under
President James Buchanan...
...and was a Confederate leader
during the Civil War.
"Bunny" had intended to undergo
a sex-change operation...
...but an auto accident prevented
him from having the procedure.
He died on November 5, 1996.
He was portrayed by actor
Bill Murray in "Ed Wood."
Dudley Manlove (Eros)
was a longtime friend of Ed's.
He also appeared in Ed's
"Final Curtain"...
and some of Ed's industrial films
for Autonetics Aviation in the 1960s.
Never a major success in film
or television...
...Manlove had great success on radio.
He passed away on April 17, 1996.
Pillow hugging is a common
reaction to feelings of loneliness.
In Japan the phenomenon has
spawned products such as...
...dakimakura "hugging pillows"
(life-size pillows with images of...
...female anime or video game
characters printed on them)...
...and the "Romantic Pillow"
available in either "boyfriend"...
...or "girlfriend" form
with a built-in arm for cuddling.
Pillow hugging is also
used in aromatherapy...
...with scented pillows serving
as the means of delivery.
Stewardess Edith is played
by Norma McCarty.
Norma married Ed in 1955 shortly
after he broke up with Dolores Fuller.
She left him after only a few weeks...
...when she learned
he was a transvestite.
The actors found the dialogue in
the cockpit scenes to be so bad...
...that most of what ended up
in the film was improvised.
This footage of Bela
was most likely shot in 1955.
Bela is wearing a cape
he had previously worn...
...in a stage production of
"'Dracula."
The cape eventually became
the property of legendary...
...horror collector and historian
Forrest J. Ackerman.
Vampira was born Maila Syrjéniemi
on December 21, 1921.
Her professional name
is Maila Nurmi.
She never made
another film for Ed...
...but she did appear in
the 1998 film based on Ed's script...
..."I Woke Up Early The Day I Died."
She first came to national
attention on her local movie show...
..."The Vampira Show,"
a.k.a. "Movie Macabre."
It was the cancellation
of that show...
...that led to her accepting
a part in "Plan 9."
In the years following she did make
a few more appearances...
...in films such as
"The Magic Sword" (1962)...
...and "Sex Kittens
Go To College" (1960).
Vampira plays a "Vampire Girl"...
...the resurrected wife
of Lugosi's character.
In "Ed Wood" she was portrayed
by actress Lisa Marie...
...who was director Tim Burton's
girlfriend at the time.
The music in "Plan 9" was not
specifically written for the film.
Like stock footage Ed made
extensive use of library music...
...for which he would only
have to pay a nominal fee...
...compared to the greater cost
of paying a composer for new music.
Joanna Lee's early career
acting in B-movies such as...
"The Brain Eaters" (1958)
and "Plan 9" (as Tanna)...
...would not seem to indicate the
great success she would later enjoy...
...as a writer for TV shows such as
"My Three Sons," "The Flintstones"...
..."Bewitched," "Gilligan's Island,"
and "The Waltons."
She was nominated for an Emmy
for the TV movie "Babe" (1975)...
...and a Director's Guild award for
"My Dad Can't Be Crazy... Can He?"...
...and won a Humanitas Prize
for the 1987 TV movie...
..."The Kid Who Wouldn't Quit:
The Brad Silverman Story."
Joanna Lee passed away on
October 24, 2003.
Carl Anthony (Patrolman Larry)
was another of Ed's friends.
He played a lead role
in Ed's last mainstream film...
..."The Sinister Urge" (1960),
a film about the porn industry.
He would only appear
in one more film...
"Raw Force" (1982)
starring Cameron Mitchell.
Conrad Brooks (Patrolman Jamie)
was born Conrad Biedrzycki
on January 3, 1931.
He first met Ed when he and his
brothers were visiting Hollywood...
...and Ed agreed to act as cameraman
in a short film for them.
This footage (some of the earliest
surviving Ed material)...
...was eventually released
on home video.
Brooks went on to appear
in six films for Ed...
...including "Glen or Glenda"
and "Bride of the Monster"...
as well as appearing in "Ed Wood"
and "I Woke Up Early The Day I Died."
Beginning in the 1980s he began
appearing in countless sub-B movies...
...from "Curse of the Queerwolf" (1988)
and "Ghost Taxi" (1999)...
...to "Dr. Horror's Erotic
House of Idiots" (2003).
Brooks was himself portrayed
by actor Brent Hinkley in "Ed Wood."
Lyle Talbot was born
Lysle Henderson on February 8, 1902.
During a career that spanned
six decades he appeared...
...in over 200 films and
over 150 television shows.
He was best known to the
general public as Joe Randolph...
...the Nelsons' next-door neighbor...
...on "The Adventures
of Ozzie and Harriet."
He appeared in many
movie serials including...
...both "Batman and Robin" (1949)
as Commissioner Gordon...
...and "Atom Man vs. Superman" (1950)
as villain Lex Luthor.
He first worked with Ed in 1953
in both "Glen or Glenda"...
...and the TV pilot
"Crossroad Avenger."
He also appeared in Ed's 1954
noir picture "Jail Bait."
His last acting role
was a guest appearance...
...on the sitcom "Newhart"
in January 1987.
Talbot passed away on
March 2, 1996.
Sightings of unknown aircraft
date as far back as 329 BC...
...when Alexander the Great's army
saw "two silver shields" in the sky.
Other historical events include
sightings in Japan in 1235...
...Nuremberg in 1561,
and Basel, Switzerland, in 1566.
The earliest sightings in the United States
date from the 1890s.
The classic UFO era began in 1947
with Kenneth Arnold's sighting...
...of several objects in the sky
over Mount Rainier, Washington.
The UFO craze really took hold
in the U.S. in the 1950s...
...with countless movies books
and comics devoted to the subject.
Although the belief in alien aircraft
has dropped off since then...
...recent polls still show that
a majority of people believe...
...that extraterrestrial aircraft
do in fact exist.
There have been many attempts to
contact extraterrestrials.
One movement devoted to
such ideas is called SETI...
...Search for Extraterrestrial
Intelligence.
The basic assumption is that any
extraterrestrial life would attempt...
...to contact us and that any
such contact would be...
...mutually beneficial.
Among the early SETI experiments
were the efforts of Frank Drake...
...at Cornell University in 1960
to contact alien life through radio.
More recent attempts have included
the use of laser and optical devices.
To date, despite these many efforts,
no concrete evidence has surfaced...
...to conclusively prove the existence
of extraterrestrial life.
Costume designer Richard Chaney
only costumed two other films:
The 1956 films "The Boss"
and "The Bold and the Brave."
He never designed again
after working on "Plan 9."
The makeup for "Plan 9" was partly
the work of Harry Thomas...
...whose career ran from 1936 until
1975 and spanned over 70 films...
...including "Superman
and the Mole Men" (1951)...
..."The Ten Commandments" (1956),
and "Little Shop of Horrors" (1960).
He also worked for Ed on
"Glen or Glenda," "Jail Bait"...
...and "Night of the Ghouls."
He was portrayed by journeyman actor
Bob Leonard Termo in "Ed Wood."
Thomas passed away on
October 21, 1996.
"Plan 9" Cinematographer
William C. Thompson...
...worked on all of Ed's films
from "Glen or Glenda" in 1953...
...in which he also played a judge...
...through "The Sinister Urge,"
Thompson's final film.
Thompson shot over 60 films
in his career...
...including non-Ed B-pictures
like "Racket Girls" (1951)...
...and Stephen Apostolof's
"Journey to Freedom" (1957).
In "Ed Wood" Thompson was portrayed
by character actor Norman Alden.
Thompson passed away on
October 22, 1963.
This is the last snippet of Lugosi
footage that appears in "Plan 9."
Paul Marco, an old friend of Ed's,
plays Patrolman Kelton.
Due to the appearance of Kelton,
"Plan 9" serves as a kind of sequel...
...to Ed's previous film,
"Bride of the Monster."
This connection is more explicit in
"Night of the Ghouls" when Kelton...
...talks about dealing with "monsters,"
"space people," and "mad doctors."
The "Kelton Trilogy" were the only
films Marco appeared in for Ed...
...although he would continue
to portray Kelton in public...
...for many years.
Watch Dr. Mason's cape.
In a moment...
...it will start to fall off but Mason
will catch it and pull it back on.
There it goes.
Ed did not believe in doing a second
take unless the first one...
...was completely unusable.
In 2005 Marco appeared as Kelton
in two independent films:
"The Naked Monster"
and "Kelton's Dark Corner."
In "Ed Wood" Marco was
portrayed by Max Casella...
...of "Doogie Howser" fame.
"Plan 9" was shot in a small
facility called Quality Studios...
...located on Santa Monica Blvd.
Next to the Harvey Hotel.
In the years since "Plan 9" was made
it has changed hands several times...
...serving in various capacities
for its different owners.
It is still standing today.
Ed Wood was born
Edward Davis Wood Jr...
on October 10, 1924,
in Poughkeepsie, New York.
He lived there until 1942,
when he enlisted in the Marines.
He served in the South Pacific,
seeing action in several battles.
He was one of only about 400
U.S. survivors of the 40,00 troops...
...who invaded the Tarawa islands
in November 1943.
Upon returning from the war
Ed studied film under the G.I. Bill.
He then made his way
to Hollywood around 1947...
...hoping to break
into the movies.
He first worked in Hollywood
for Universal Studios...
...as a "production assistant"
on many B-grade films.
It was there that Ed first met
actors such as Lyle Talbot.
His first professional work was for
a production company he founded...
...with Crawford John Thomas
to make TV commercials.
Ed produced over 150 commercials,
according to his 1950s résumé.
Ed's first feature film was 1953's
"Glen or Glenda."
He followed that in 1954 with
the noir-style crime drama "Jail Bait"...
that introduced future "Hercules"
actor Steve Reeves.
After "Plan 9" Ed directed
only one more feature:
1960's "The Sinister Urge,"
although he would also direct...
...a few nudie and adult films
in the late '60s/early '70s.
The last film Ed directed was
the 1971 porn film "Necromania"...
a tale of two young lovers
with sex problems...
...played by real-life couple
Ric Lutze and Rene Bond...
...who seek the help of
a sorceress to relieve their troubles.
Most of Ed's output post:
"Plan 9" was as a screenwriter.
He wrote or co-wrote
over half a dozen movies...
...for exploitation director
Stephen Apostolof...
...and several more
for other directors.
Ed also acted throughout
those years...
...appearing in small
parts for Apostolof...
...as well as starring in
the 1969 comic nudie film...
"The Love Feast,"
a.k.a. "Pretty Models All In A Row."
Ed wrote several "adult" novels
to pay the bills in the '60s and '70s.
These included titles such as:
"Black Lace Drag,"
a.k.a. "Killer In Drag,."
"Death of a Transvestite,"
a.k.a. "Let Me Die In Drag,."
"Devil Girls," "Hell Chicks,"
"Security Risk"...
...as well as two novels on
the Watts uprisings:
'Watts... The Difference"
and 'Watts..After."
Among Ed's last commissioned work
was a script for director...
...Fred Olen Ray entitled
"Beach Blanket Bloodbath."
The script was never completed
but Ray shot some footage...
...based on the material on the set
of his 1988 film "Star Slammer."
Ed and Kathy Wood were evicted
from their apartment in 1978...
...and went to live with actor
Peter Coe.
It was while staying there that
Edward D. Wood Jr. passed away...
...on December 10, 1978,
at age 54.
Since its release "Plan 9"
as shown up all over the world.
Some of its alternate titles are:
"Plan 9 Aus Dem Weltall" (Germany)
i.e. "Plan 9 From The Universe"...
..."Vampiros del Espacio" (Argentina)
i.e. "Vampires from Space"...
..."Espectros del Espacio" (Brazil)
i.e. "Spectres from Space"...
..."Plano 9 do Vampiro Zombie" (Portugal)
i.e. "Plan 9 of the Zombie Vampire."
In the 1980s "Plan 9" served as
the basis for a musical called...
...appropriately enough
"Plan Nine: The Musical."
It added a great deal
of intentional humor...
...and sexual innuendo
not found in the original.
In 1990 Malibu Comics published
a comic book adaptation of "Plan"
while Eternity comics put out
an "official" sequel a year later:
"Plan 9 From Outer Space:
Thirty Years Later."
In 1990 Malibu also published
the screenplay to "Plan 9."
It was sold as being
"Original Uncensored and Uncut."
It was edited by Tom Mason
and most likely based on his copy.
In 1993 a pornographic parody
of "Plan 9" was produced entitled...
..."Plan 69 From Outer Space."
Although it does not follow
the same plot as "Plan"
it has many similarities.
These include scenes set in an
unconvincing cockpit on a patio...
...and in a woman's bedroom.
The aliens fly a spaceship that looks
suspiciously like a paper plate...
...and are reviving the dead
for their own nefarious plans.
It was followed by a remake
of "Glen or Glenda" entitled...
..."Glen and Glenda" which adhered
more closely to the originals plot...
...even to the point of using Ed's
own dialogue in several scenes.
In 2005 a video game called
"Destroy All Humans!" was released...
...that featured unlockable footage
from "Plan 9 From Outer Space."
In 1981 "Plan 9" was named
'Worst Film of All Time"...
...in the book
"The Golden Turkey Awards."
"In the same book Ed was named
'Worst Director of All Time."
Despite these "awards"
(or perhaps because of them)...
...Ed's popularity has only
grown over the years.
His films see regular release
on home video and DVD...
...there are film festivals
dedicated to his work...
...and his life has been
documented on shows such as...
"The Incredibly Strange
Film Show" (in 1989)...
..."Mysteries and Scandals"
(in 1999)...
...and in the film "Ed Wood" where
he was played by Johnny Depp.
"Ed Wood" was a box office failure
but won two Academy Awards:
The first for makeup...
...the second for Martin Landau 's
portrayal of Bela.
Memorabilia from Ed's movies
regularly runs to hundreds...
...(if not thousands) of dollars.
Even his cheap sleazy novels have
become valuable collector's items.
With Ed's filmography being regularly
revisited (particularly "Plan 9")...
...he and his films continue
to garner new fans year after year.
His legacy seems assured and his work
will likely never be forgotten.